<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from Turkie. Or a true and perfect relation sent from Constantinople Touching the death of Achmet the last emperour of the Turkes. As also the miraculous deliuerances of Mustapha, (brother to the said Achmet then emperour,) and his strang escapes from his purposed death. Together with the memorable accesse of the said Mustapha into the Turkish empire, and a narration of such things as haue since happened.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848431</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13524</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13524)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1672:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from Turkie. Or a true and perfect relation sent from Constantinople Touching the death of Achmet the last emperour of the Turkes. As also the miraculous deliuerances of Mustapha, (brother to the said Achmet then emperour,) and his strang escapes from his purposed death. Together with the memorable accesse of the said Mustapha into the Turkish empire, and a narration of such things as haue since happened.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones for Samuell Nealand, and Nathaniell Browne and are to be sould at the great North-dore of Saint Paules Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B³ (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; tightly bound affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mustafa --  I, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1591-1639.</term>
               <term>Ahmed --  I, --  Sultan of the Turks, 1590-1617.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13524:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:13524:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
            <p>Newes from Turkie. <hi>OR</hi> A true and perfect Relation ſent from CONSTANTINOPLE.</p>
            <p>Touching the death of <hi>Achmet</hi> the laſt Emperour of the Turkes.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO THE MIRACVLOVS deliuerances of MVSTAPHA, (brother to the ſaid ACHMET then Emperour,) and his ſtrang <hi>eſcapes frrm his purpoſed death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the memorable acceſſe of the ſaid MVSTAPHA into the Turkiſh Empire, and a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſuch things as haue ſince <hi>happened.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Iones</hi> for <hi>Samuell Nealand,</hi> and <hi>Nathaniell Browne</hi> and are to be ſould at the great North-dore of Saint <hi>Paules</hi> Church. 1618.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13524:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 128 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:13524:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 128 -->
            <head>A RELATION SENT from Conſtantinople touching <hi>the death of</hi> Achmett <hi>the laſt Emperour of the</hi> Turkes. As alſo the memorable acceſſe of <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tapha his brother to the ſaid Turkiſh Empire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ahumet</hi> 3 of that name the fourtenth <hi>Emperour</hi> of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> departing this life in the yeare 1602 left two children behind him, which he had of the <hi>Sultane Flatra</hi> a <hi>Cipriote</hi> Ladie; the elder whereof was named <hi>Achmett,</hi> and the yonger <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, Achmett</hi> the elder of the age of fifteenth yeares was at that time reſident in <hi>Magneſia</hi> the ordinary Appennage and entertainment of the elder children, and future ſucceſſors of the <hi>Sultane Ottomans,</hi> from whence he was ſent for with all diligence by the <hi>Baſſaes</hi> to take the poſſeſſion of the Throne of his late father which accordingly he did, and was the firſt Emperour of that name, and the fifteenth
<pb facs="tcp:13524:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 129 -->of the race of the <hi>Ottomans</hi> contained from the father to the ſonne euen to this time.</p>
            <p>Now for as much as it is the Cuſtome of the Turkiſh Emperours, that entring into their Empire: they put to death by the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their brothers and Nephewes, without leaving any Male in life, but onely ſuch as ſaue themſelues by flight, as ſometimes it happens.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe the <hi>Baſſaes,</hi> and other great ones of the <hi>Ottoman port</hi> were of opinion, not to ſuffer, that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> brother of <hi>Achmet</hi> ſhould runne this fortune; and that by a Councell of eſtate, becauſe that ſeeing their Emperour <hi>Achmet</hi> to be only aged fifteene yeares, they were affraid that he comming to faile in this younger age and leauing no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren able to gouerne, the eſtate might come to be troubled and weakned by Ciuil warres.</p>
            <p>It was therfore Decreed that <hi>Muſtahpas</hi> life ſhould be conſerued, but in ſuch meanes that he ſhould be retained priſoner in there Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the <hi>Seraile</hi> of the Emperor at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> vnder ſure garde.</p>
            <p>During the firſt yeares of the impriſonment of <hi>Muſtapha</hi> there was nothing cruell decreed againſt him, by reaſon of the minority of the <hi>Sultan,</hi> but when that <hi>Achmet</hi> ſawe that he had Children, many times he propoſed to his Councell the putting to death of his brother
<pb facs="tcp:13524:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 129 -->and it ſeemeth miraculous that the ſame Councell came not to effect. For among other times it is reported that one euening his death hauing beene determined and appointed to be executed the day following, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Achmet</hi> found himſelfe all the night long ſo troubled with apparitions and hidious dreames, that the day being come, he ſayd, ſeeing that the onely reſolution of putting his brother to death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had ſo troubled him, he did beleeue that his paine and torment would be much encreaſed, if he ſhould execute his purpoſe, and therefore he commaunded, that his brother ſhould liue.</p>
            <p>Another time, <hi>Achmet</hi> being in a window of his <hi>Seraile</hi> beheld <hi>Muſtapha</hi> his brother who by his lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was walking in the gardens with his Guarde. One that was neere to <hi>Achmet</hi> ſaid vnto him that it was a matter of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous concequenſe to let him haue that liberty Vpon which diſcourſe <hi>Achmet</hi> entering into choller (through diſtruſt) tooke his Bowe (which he could drawe with great dexterity <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd good ayme) and bending the ſame with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Arrowe couched, he aymed at his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her to ſticke him but at the very inſtant he <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elt ſo great paine in his arme and ſhoulder, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat being not able to execute his purpoſe, he
<pb facs="tcp:13524:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 130 -->ſaid with a loud voice that God would not that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> ſhould dy.</p>
            <p>This Prince during his detencion and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in the three chambers of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caile</hi> which hath laſted fifteene yeares hath paſſed the time in a deuout and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue life after the manner of the <hi>Muſulmans,</hi> not delighting himſelfe in any other exerciſe and paſſetime but in reading of the <hi>Arabian</hi> bookes of their Doctors in diuers ſciences.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the <hi>Grand-ſignor</hi> did permit him to walke in his gardens with his Guard, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe called him to the affaires of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to take councell with him, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times followed his aduiſes, becauſe he knew him of a good iudgment and very deepe.</p>
            <p>After this long time and this ſo long appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hention of death <hi>Achmet</hi> the firſt of that name, and the fifteenth Emperor of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> race being grieuouſly ſicke in the Month of <hi>Nouember</hi> 1617 in his <hi>Secaile</hi> of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> was giuen to vnderſtand by thoſe that were about him that he ſhould doe well to thinke vpon the ſucceſſion of his Empire.</p>
            <p>He had Children of the <hi>Sultane</hi> his wife which were in ſo yong an age that there was no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> apparance for looking that way, and beſides this <hi>Sultane</hi> was dead, ſo as none would ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:13524:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 130 -->for the Children; but on the other part the <hi>Sultane Harachie</hi> mother of the <hi>Emperour</hi> and of <hi>Muſtapha</hi> was yet liuing, who fearing that if the Children of the <hi>Emperour</hi> were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the gouerment &amp; that during their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age the <hi>Baſſaies</hi> ſhould take the authoritie of the gouerme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, there would not, remaine for her any honor or dignitie, this was the reaſon that ſhe inclined on the ſide of <hi>Muſtapha</hi> &amp; ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited the ſicke <hi>Emperour</hi> to name him for his ſucceſſor. Wherefore the 15 of the ſaid month of <hi>Nouember</hi> 1617. the <hi>Emperour Achmet</hi> ſeeing himſelfe neere his end, &amp; without hope of life, he ſent for his brother <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and told him that foreſeeing that God would otherwiſe diſpoſe of him, he deſired before he died to prouide for the conſeruation of the Empire, and to that end had choſen him for his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, praying him to take into his hands the gouernment immediatly after his death. <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tapha</hi> very much aſtoniſhed at ſuch diſcourſes, made him anſwer with words full of feare and humility that he might not accept of that honour which he did him, ſeeing that of right and by iuſtice the Empire belonged to his eldeſt ſonne. Whereunto <hi>Achment</hi> replied that his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne had neither age nor capacity to take it vpon him; and that he would acquit
<pb facs="tcp:13524:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->himſelfe of that charge better, and that it was neceſſary for the maintenance of this ſo great a Monarchie that he ſhould take the direction and managing thereof; recommending to him his Childrin that he had by the <hi>Sultane,</hi> and praying him to afford them the ſame treatment and vſage that he had receiued from him, leauing the other Children which he had of women that were his ſlaues to his diſcreſſion. A little after <hi>Achmet</hi> had vttered theſe words he rendred vp his ſpirit &amp; <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> was acknowledged by all for the ſucceſſor to the Turkiſh Empire, who at his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Crowne found himſelfe ſo ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed that he thought he had been in a dreame, to ſee himſelfe from a ſtraight capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity and a continuall apprehenſion of death to be lifted vp to ſo great and Soueraigne a power. This Prince is aged about twenty three yeares, of a faire proportion, greate and ſtraight, meager and pale with a blacke beard.</p>
            <p>Since the deceaſe of <hi>Achmet</hi> there hath not happened any change in the gouerment. The Emperour <hi>Muſtapha</hi> ſhewes himſelfe a louer of peace with his neighbours. So ſoone as he was entred into poſſeſſion of the Empire he cauſed to be ſet at liberty the Ambaſſadour of the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> whom his predeſeſſor had
<pb facs="tcp:13524:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 131 -->cauſed to be ſtaied contrary to the publike faith, vnder cullour that during his aboad at the Port of the Graund Signear there were come ſome newes of ſtures and troubles rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the <hi>Perſian.</hi> Which being done, <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> diſpached onein all dilligence toward the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uda</hi> in <hi>Hungerie</hi> commanding him to abſerſt and entertaine inuiolately the Treatis made by his prediſeſſors with the Emperour <hi>Mathias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God open the eyes of the vnderſtanding of this Prince &amp; make him know how much he is bound to his deuine Maieſtie who hath mortified and quickened him, and from the ſhadowes of death hath raiſed him vpon one of the higheſt Thrones of the world, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him thankes for the ſame. Not after the <hi>Muſulman</hi> faſhion, enimie to the croſſe of our Sauionr, but in the boſome of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Catholicke Church, out of which there is no ſaluation.</p>
            <p>For if the Lord ſhould once open his eyes, be ſhould ſee what wrongs, and iniuries his predeſeſſors haue done againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in ſhedding innocent bloud. With his ſword, what Landes, Nations, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, what Empires, Kingdomes, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, with Citties inumerable hath bee
<pb facs="tcp:13524:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->wonne from the Chriſtians: Yea, then hee ſhall ſee, that where Gods word hath beene truly preached, and the Sacraments admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, there his predeceſſors haue ſet vp bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>Mahomet</hi> with his erronious <hi>Alchoran</hi> quite ouerthrowing the flouriſhing Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> the learned Churches in <hi>Grecia,</hi> the manifolde Churches of <hi>Africa,</hi> yea all Churches where the diligent Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> with others of the Apoſtles ſo labouringly by preaching &amp; writing planted, haue beene vtterly defaced by his predeceſſors: As in all the Kingdomes of <hi>Syria, Paleſtine, Arabia, Perſia,</hi> in all <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> with the Empire of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> yea, through the compaſſe of <hi>Aſia,</hi> with <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> they haue ſubdued. Alſo let him looke into <hi>Europe,</hi> there he ſhall alſo ſee, how all <hi>Thraſia,</hi> with the Empire of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> all <hi>Grecia, Cyprus, Ilyricum,</hi> and not long ſince, almoſt all the whole Kingdome of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> with much of <hi>Auſtria:</hi> All theſe Nations, Countries, Empires, Kingdomes, Prouinces, with their famous Citties, haue they ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with lamentable ſlaughter of Chriſtian and that bloudily.</p>
            <p>It is neceſſary for all Chriſtians to knowe the Storie of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> their cruell tyranny &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13524:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 132 -->bloudie victories, with the vtter ruine of ſo many chriſtian Churches: for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 For the better explayning of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in the ſcriptures, ſhewing his overthrow.</item>
               <item>2 That we may learne thereby, either with the publike Church to lament with our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſuch a great decay of chriſtian faith by theſe wicked <hi>Turke:</hi> or elſe may feare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our owne danger.</item>
               <item>3 That we may ponder more deepely with our ſelues the ſcourge of God for our ſinnes, and corrupt liues, and for our better admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to amend our liues.</item>
               <item>4 The conſideration of the horrible perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> chiefely riſeth through diſcordes and diſſentions among chriſtians themſelues, may reduce vs to ioyne together in chriſtian patience and concord.</item>
               <item>5 But cheifely theſe great victoryes of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and vnproſperous ſpeed of chriſtians fighting againſt them: may admoniſh and teach vs, following the example of the old Iſraelites, how to ſeeke for greater ſtrength to encounter with theſe enemyes of Chriſt, then hitheto hath bin done.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt we muſt conſider, that the whole po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Satan the Prince of this world, goeth with the <hi>Turkes,</hi> which to reſiſt, no ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:13524:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->of mans arme is ſufficient, but onely the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, going with vs in our battels. As among the old <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> the <hi>Arke</hi> of Gods <hi>Couenaunt</hi> and promiſe went with them alſo fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their enemyes: for it is true that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>without me yee can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> other wiſe: there is no puiſſance to with ſtand the Deuill, or to conquour the world, but onely our faith: to which all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God (touching ſaluation) be annexed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beyond which promiſes we muſt not goe.</p>
            <p>Now it behoueth euery good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to call vpon God that be would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found the enemyes of his Church, and then wee ſhould ſoone ſee the effect of our prayers, with the vtter ouerthrow of thoſe that are enemys to the croſſe of Chriſt. Which we intreat the Lord to bring to paſſe for his owne glory, and for the ioy and comfort of the Saincts, through our Lord &amp; Sauiour <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſus Chriſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13524:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 133 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
